Guide to the Wesleyan Museum Records, 1836 - 1985
Wesleyan Museum Records, 1836 - 1985
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)
2000-27
9.25
12
The Wesleyan Museum was created in 1871 to supplement the science curriculum at Wesleyan University. Its collections of natural history materials as well as enthnographic artifacts made it popular with students and faculty in the late 19th century. It became less important to the university as new methods of studying supplanted the museum, and it was closed in 1957.
The Wesleyan Museum Records contains annual reports, correspondence, invoices, inventories, catalogues, accession books, photos, and other materials related to the operations and collections of the museum.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions. Some of the bound albums are fragile and should be handled with care.
Acquisitions Information
Materials were transferred from the Geology Department in August 1984.
Historical Note
The Wesleyan Museum (1871-1957) was an integral part of the science curriculum at Wesleyan University. Materials collected by faculty, students, and other donors were intended to help students study the natural world. Materials collected included shells, rocks, fossils, wood specimens, mineral specimens, birds, fish, animals, insects, and dried plants. In addition, American Indian artifacts, coins, certain artworks, and a mummy also found a home in the museum. Wesleyan closely followed the 19th century curiosity cabinet model of natural history museums.
The Museum opened on the third and fourth floors of Judd Hall in 1871. By the end of the decade, a number of students and faculty members were using the museum's materials in their research. It later expanded into some rooms on the second floor of the building in 1886. In the late 1880s, the museum added a focus on ethnological collections, related to humans.
Towards the end of the 1890s, the institution's interest in the museum lessened, with less funding alotted. The museum moved out of the second floor of Judd Hall. New faculty preferred laboratory work to studying museum specimens, and the museum became less relevant to the curriculum. The Museum remained open but largely unused in the curriculum.
In 1938, the museum had an offical re-opening to signify renewed interest in the museum. Funds were alocated for repairs and remodeling. School groups regularly toured the museum, and were perhaps its primary visitors until the Museum closed in 1957.
When the Wesleyan Museum closed, there were thousands of specimens to disperse. Many went to the Smithsonian Institution; others were donated or put on loan to Connecticut institutions. Some of the materials were divided up among science departments at Wesleyan. Other materials were dispersed to storage locations across campus, often without a record of the transfer.
In the 1970s, some faculty took an interest in cataloging the materials within their own departments, especially archaeological and anthropological materials. The museum's mummy came to national prominence in the late 1970s when it was unwrapped and studied by Professor Stephen Dyson.
Collection Overview
The Wesleyan Museum Records contains annual reports, correspondence, invoices, inventories, catalogues, accession books, photos, and other materials. It is organized into four series.
Series 1 contains Annual Reports of the museum. Series 2 contains Administrative materials, such as correspondence, used in the daily operations of the museum. Series 3, the largest series, is Accessions, Catalogues and Inventories. These materials reflect the museum's natural history focus, with many bird, fish, mammal and insect specimens. There are also detailed lists of shells, minerals, wood samples, coins, marbles, and even a detailed description of the museum's mummy. There are also catalogs of some of the curiosities donated to the museum by collectors or groups. Series 4 is Images, a small collection of photographs and negatives.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Curricula.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--History.; Museum exhibits--History.; Museum techniques--History.; Anthropological museums and collections--History.; Museums--Acquisitions.; Museums and schools.; Museums--Connecticut--Middletown--History.; Natural history museums--History.; Photographs.
Related Material
Vertical Files, Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Detailed Description of the Collection
- Series 1. Annual Reports, 1877-1973
  The Annual Reports contain summaries of changes in administration or procedure, major acquisitions, number of visitors, and any other notable happenings. The reports from the 1970s relate to the anthropology and archaeology collections, some of which came from the original Wesleyan Museum.
  In most cases, the photocopies of the 1877-1892 annual reports should be used to prevent wear and tear on the originals.
  - Original reports (Box 1)
    - Complete set in book box, 1877-1892
    - Fifth and Sixth Annual Reports, including a history of the museum from its formation, 1877 (Folder 1)
    - Eighth Annual Report, 1879 (Folder 2)
    - Ninth Annual Report, 1880 (Folder 3)
    - Tenth Annual Report, 1881 (Folder 4)
    - Eleventh Annual Report, 1882 (Folder 5)
    - Twelfth Annual Report, 1883 (Folder 6)
    - Thirteenth Annual Report, 1884 (Folder 7)
    - Fourteenth Annual Report, 1885 (Folder 8)
    - Fifteenth Annual Report, 1886 (Folder 9)
    - Seventeenth Annual Report, 1888 (Folder 10)
    - Eighteenth Annual Report, 1889 (Folder 11)
    - Nineteenth Annual Report, 1890 (Folder 12)
    - Twentieth Annual Report, 1891 (Folder 13)
    - Twenty-First Annual Report, 1892 (Folder 14)
    - Annual Report, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Annual Report, 1938 (Folder 2)
    - Annual Report, 1948 (Folder 3)
    - Annual Report, 1957 (Folder 4)
    - Annual Report, 1970-1971 (Folder 5)
    - Annual Report, February 1972 (Folder 6)
    - Annual Report, 1972-1973 (Folder 7)
  - Photocopies of reports
    - Fifth and Sixth Annual Reports, including a history of the museum from its formation, 1877 (Folder 8)
    - Seventh Annual Report, 1878 (Folder 9)
    - Eighth Annual Report, 1879 (Folder 10)
    - Ninth Annual Report, 1880 (Folder 11)
    - Tenth Annual Report, 1881 (Folder 12)
    - Eleventh Annual Report, 1882 (Folder 13)
    - Twelfth Annual Report, 1883 (Folder 14)
    - Thirteenth Annual Report, 1884 (Folder 15)
    - Fourteenth Annual Report, 1885 (Folder 16)
    - Fifteenth Annual Report, 1886 (Folder 17)
    - Sixteenth Annual Report, 1887 (Folder 18)
    - Seventeenth Annual Report, 1888 (Folder 19)
    - Eighteenth Annual Report, 1889 (Folder 20)
    - Nineteenth Annual Report, 1890 (Folder 21)
    - Twentieth Annual Report, 1891 (Folder 22)
    - Twenty-First Annual Report, 1892 (Folder 23)
- Series 2. Administrative, 1836-1985
  Administrative materials include correspondence, reports, forms, registers of visitors, and other documents used in the administration of museum operations.
  - Correspondence and administrative documents
    - 1836-1896 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - 1911-1927 (Folder 2)
    - 1930-1956 (Folder 3)
    - 1957-1985 (Folder 4)
    - Undated (Folder 5)
  - Exhibit and item labels (Folder 6)
  - Loans (Folder 7)
  - Scrapbook (Box 4)
    This item is fragile and must be handled with care. It contains correspondence and invoices dating from 1876 to 1896.
  - The Archaeological Collection of the United States National Museum, in Charge of the Smithsonian Institution, Washington D.C., by Charles Rau
    This volume has a hole drilled through its upper lefthand corner and a chain threaded through the hole. The book was possibly used as a reference book for the employees or visitors of the Wesleyan Museum.
  - Supply catalogs (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Registers of Visitors
    - 1874-1896 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1896-1929 (Folder 2)
    - 1938-1952 (Folder 3)
- Series 3. Accessions, Catalogues, and Inventories
  New accessions to the museum, organized by genre, were carefully recorded by hand in bound volumes or notebooks. Each accession was assigned a number.
  Catalogues are inventories of particular collections, usually assembled by a single collector or small group of collectors.
  Inventories are lists or descriptions of items in the museum.
  These materials reflect the museum's natural history focus, with many bird, fish, mammal and insect specimens. There are also detailed lists of shells, minerals, wood samples, coins, marbles, and even a detailed description of the museum's mummy. There are also catalogs of some of the curiosities donated to the museum by collectors or groups; for example, the Missionary Lyceum, an 19th century Wesleyan student group, recorded African, Indian, and South American materials in their Catalogue of Curiosities.
  - Accessions
    - Articulata: Crustacean Vermes (Box 6, Folder 1)
      - Book 1, no. 1-360
      - Book 2, no. 361-720
      - Book 3, no. 721-760
    - Articulata: Insects and Arachnids (Folder 2)
      - Book 1, No. 1-360
      - Book 2, No. 361-720
      - Book 4, No. 1081-1440 (2 copies)
      - Book 5, No. 1441-1800
      - Book 6, No. 1801-2160
      - Book 7, No. 2161-2219
    - Birds (Folder 3)
      - Book 2, no. 361-720
      - Book 3, no. 721-1080
      - Book 4, no. 1081-1440
      - Book 5, no. 1441-1770
      - Book 6, no. 1771-2130
      - Book 7, no. 2131-2422
    - Birds: nests and eggs (Folder 4)
      - Book 1, no. 1-360
      - Book 2, no. 361-479
      - Discarded book 2, no. 361-
    - Botany (Folder 5)
      - Book 1, no. 1-360
      - Book 2, no. 361-689
      - Book 3, no. 691-782
    - Fishes (Folder 6)
      - Book 1, no. 1-360
      - Book 2, no. 361-720
      - Book 3, no. 721-1090
    - Insecta [Rhopalocera] and heterocera (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Book 1, no. 1-210
      - Book 2, no. 211-342
    - Mammalia (Folder 2)
      - Book 1, no. 1-360
      - Book 2, no. 361-690
      - Book 2, no. 361-646 (copied)
    - Mollusca
      - Bound catalogue, no. 1-3570 (Box 8)
      - Bound catalogue, no. 3571-7190
      - Book 1, no. 7191-7550 (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Book 1, no. 7191-7550 (copied)
      - No. 7191-7786, Plants no. 398-458 (copied)
      - Book 2, no. 7551-7854
    - Protozoa (Folder 4)
      - Book 1
    - Radiata (Folder 5)
      - Book 1, no. 1-360
        Book 1 only goes to number 280. 80 numbers not filled.
      - Book 2, no. 361-600
      - Book 3, no. 601-811
    - Reptilia and amphibia (Folder 6)
      - Book 1, no. 1-360
      - Book 2, no. 361-720
      - Book 3, no. 721-783
    - Vertebrata (Folder 7)
      - Book 1, Recatalogued
        These specimens have been re-catalogued in the special Catalogues of Mammals, Birds, Reptiles and Amphibia, and Fishes.
    - Loose page, unidentified (Folder 8)
    - Deaccessions (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Catalogues
    - Barratt Cabinet (Folder 2)
    - Curiosities belonging to the Missionary Lyceum, June 1848 (Folder 3)
      Made by Benjamin T. Roberts, Frank O. Blair, Ralza M. Manly, and Henry S. Noyes.
    - Cuvicarian Cabinet, March 24, 1838 (Folder 4)
      Arranged by A. Bigelow, S. Martindale, Jr. and S. Fitch, Jr., Committee.
    - Frankfort Cabinet (Folder 5)
    - Minerals, Wesleyan University (Folder 6)
    - Minerals, Wesleyan University, May 1838 (Folder 7)
    - Minerals from Prescott Cabinets (Folder 8)
    - Collection of woods from the Charles H. Neff collection (Folder 9)
      Woods found growing about Portland, Conn., or vicinity.
    - Local collection of Charles H. Neff (Box 10, Folder 1)
      All Indian relics recorded in this book were found about Portland, Conn., and in the neighboring towns within a radius of a few miles.
    - Sea shell collection of Charles H. Neff, Portland, Conn. (Folder 2)
    - A complete list of stuffed birds and mammals in collection of Charles H. Neff (Folder 3)
    - Field notes of Charles H. Neff, 1874-1910 (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - Inventory
    - Birds of Connecticut (Folder 2)
    - Coin collections (Folder 3)
    - Marbles (Folder 4)
    - Mummy (Folder 5)
    - General (Folder 6)
    - Old artifact lists (Folder 7)
    - Items sent to National Museum (Folder 8)
- Series 4. Images
  The photographs include images from a dig in Tennessee, shrunken heads, and a person dressed in an Inuit costume, as well as images of the museum and some of its items. These appear to be from the early 20th century. There are also several photographs from the 1970s of a mortar the was uncovered in Portland, Connecticut.
  The negatives include images of pottery and Brazilian, Polynesian, and Egyptian materials.
  The series also contains X-rays of the Wesleyan museum mummy.
  - Photographs (Folder 9-11)
  - Negatives (Folder 12)
  - Oversize Photographs (Box 12)
  - X-rays
    The x-rays appear to be images of the museum mummy from 1978.